A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Mark Elliott FA1713
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Mark Elliott
1965-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Elliott, Mark
Ford Foundation
FA1713
11.11 Cubic Feet 29 Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Mark Elliott who worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program during the early to mid-1990s. The collection is comprised of one series of subject files. Elliott's subject files document his activities for managing grants to housing and economic development programs, research studies, and projects as well as his participation in the Urban Poverty Program's planning and strategizing efforts. Materials within the collection extend back from before Elliott's tenure at the Foundation up until the point where the Urban Poverty Program was set to transition to become part of the new Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996.
The collection chiefly consists of correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, reports, press clippings, newsletters, brochures, publications, schedules, agendas, and Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs). Documents show that during Elliot's tenure as a Program Officer, the Urban Poverty Program supported and engaged with organizations and projects concerned with economic development, community development, housing, employment and job training, housing discrimination and segregation, urban reinvestment, and anti-poverty strategies.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:114.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series of subject files. The records' creators imposed an inconsistent alphabetical arrangement on the files.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1965-1996
Biographical / Historical
Founder and President of the Economic Mobility Corporation, Mark Elliott has made a career in both public service and philanthropy. During the early to mid-1990s, he worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program where he was responsible for managing the Foundation's grants to housing and economic development projects.
Elliott founded the Economic Mobility Corporation in 2007. In addition to his work with the Ford Foundation and Mobility, he has served as Deputy Budget Director of the City of New York and worked as an executive vice president for Public/Private Ventures.
Ford Foundation; Community development; Community development corporations; Community development, Urban; Discrimination in housing; Economic development; Employment; Housing; Housing policy; Low-income housing; Minorities -- Housing; Occupational training
- Subject files, 1965-1996; 1; 11.11 Cubic Feet 28 LTR size and 1 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Mark Elliott created when he worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program. The files document the Foundation's support of programs, research studies, and projects concerned with economic development, community development, housing, homeownership, employment and job training, housing preservation, minority owned businesses, housing discrimination and segregation, self-sufficiency, urban reinvestment, and anti-poverty strategies. Common material formats found throughout the series include correspondence, memos, reports, drafts, notes, press clippings, newsletters, brochures, publications, agendas, schedules, and Recommended Grant Actions records (RGAs). Although Elliott served as a Program Officer in the 1990s, his files include material from as early as 1965. These records document the Urban Poverty Program's earlier work that extended into Elliott's tenure as well as older research papers and articles that Elliott acquired.
  Elliott's correspondence chiefly consists of communications with grantees and potential grantees, staff members from the Urban Poverty Program and the larger Ford Foundation, and other individuals involved with the housing and urban economic development fields. The series' contents show the impact of national public housing legislation and policy on the programs seeking and receiving Foundation support and on the urban economic development field with which Elliott engaged. Many records discuss the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) and the housing policies of the George H. W. Bush and Bill Clinton Presidential Administrations.
  In addition to the files documenting Elliott's responsibilities for managing the Ford Foundation's housing and economic development grants, there are several files in the series that regard the planning and strategizing of the Urban Poverty Program. Among this material is a group of records which discuss the transitioning of the Urban Poverty Program to become part of the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996.
  - Berresford, Susan V., 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bratt, Rachel - Tufts University, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Building Bridges, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business development, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business and Professional People for the Public Interest (BPI), 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community development corporations history, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Community Development Corporation of Boston, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - California Housing Partnership Corporation, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Center for Community Change, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Center for Community Self-Help, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Center for Housing Policy, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Civil society, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Edna McConnell Clark Foundation, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions (COHRE), 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Center for Policy Alternatives, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Center for Neighborhood Technology, 1993 October 8 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Center for Urban Economic Development, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Chicago Urban Poverty and Family Life Conference, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Childcare/Economic development, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Children's Defense Fund (CDF), 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Transitions to Civil Society, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Center for Law and Social Policy (CLASP), 1995 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Coalition of Community Development Financial Institutions (CDFI Coalition), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Collaboration - Education and Culture and Urban Poverty Programs, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Committee for Boston Public Housing, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Committee for Economic Development (CED), 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 32-35)
  - Competitive Communities Initiative, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Community Builders - Worcester, Massachusetts, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Lemann, Nicholas - Community development, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Ten Community Development Case Studies, 1992 November 25 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Community Development Research Center (CDRC), 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
  - Community organizing, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Community Reinvestment Act, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Community Training and Assistance Center (CTAC), 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Communication strategy, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Comprehensive Community Revitalization Program (CCRP), 1994-1996 (Box 5, Folder 47-48)
  - Comprehensive community planning initiatives, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - The Conference Board, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Conservation Company, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Consortium for Housing and Asset Management, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Corporation for Enterprise Development (CFED), 1989-1993 (Box 6, Folder 53-54)
  - Council of State Community Development Agencies (COSCDA)/APWA, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Council of Governors' Policy Advisors (CGPA), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Culture, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Andrew Cuomo Commission on Homelessness, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Daycare, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Coastal Enterprises, Inc. (CEI), 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 60-61)
  - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Greater Detroit Employment Opportunity Association, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Developing Countries Programs, 1991-1994 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Devolution, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Dudley Street Neighborhood Initiative (DSNI), 1988-1992 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Downs, Anthony, 1992-1994 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Earned income tax credit (EITC), 1993 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - National Center for Economic Alternatives (NCEA), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Economic development information, 1987-1994 (Box 8, Folder 70-72)
  - Economic development information, 1991-1996 (Box 8, Folder 73-74)
  - Egypt, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Elliott, Mark - Consulting work, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Ellwood, David T., 1986 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Economic Policy Institute (EPI), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 78-80)
  - Enterprise Foundation, 1982-1995 (Box 9, Folder 81-83)
  - Environmental materials, general, undated (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Environmental Quality International (EQI), 1994 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Earned income credit (EIC), 1994 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Expiring use, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Fair housing, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - The Family Support Act (FSA), 1991-1994 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - Fannie Mae, 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Farley, Reynolds, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Federal Financial Support of Business, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Federal Housing Administration (FHA), 1992 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Food Research Action Center (FRAC), 1991-1994 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Fordham Bedford Housing Corporation (FBHC), 1993 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Ford Foundation initiative, undated (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Foundation grants for housing and economic development, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Gateway/University of North Carolina, 1990-1995 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Government Spending to Aid the Poor, undated (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Governance, 1991-1995 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - University of Michigan - General Assistance Evaluation, 1991-1994 (Box 11, Folder 101-103)
  - Grinker, William J. - Urban job creation proposal, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Habitat II: Second United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, 1991-1996 (Box 12, Folder 105-109)
  - Habitat II: Second United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - Harlem Urban Development Corporation, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 111)
  - Hartung, Bill, 1993-1995 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Harvard Institute for International Development (HIID), 1995 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Heron Foundation, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Housing Assistance Council (HAC), 1990-1994 (Box 13, Folder 115-118)
  - Housing - Daycare, 1990-1994 (Box 13, Folder 119)
  - History of housing policy, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 120)
  - Housing information, 1991-1993 (Box 14, Folder 121-123)
  - Housing preservation, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Housing mobility, undated (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Housing trust funds, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 126)
  - United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 127)
  - Kansas City, Missouri, Housing Authority of, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 128)
  - Kain, John, undated (Box 14, Folder 129)
  - Kenya Community Development Foundation, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 130)
  - Leadership Council for Metropolitan Open Communities, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 131)
  - Lake Parc Place, 1991-1993 (Box 15, Folder 132)
  - Low Income Housing Information Service (LIHIS) - National Housing Policy Initiative (NHPI), 1989-1994 (Box 15, Folder 133-136)
  - Los Angeles Manufacturing Action Project (LAMAC), 1995 (Box 15, Folder 137)
  - Low Income Housing Information Service (LIHIS), 1991-1994 (Box 15, Folder 138-139)
  - Local Initiatives Managed Assets Corporation (LIMAC), 1992 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Low Income Housing Fund, 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Low income housing tax credit, 1995 (Box 16, Folder 142)
  - Local Initiatives Support Coalition (LISC), 1982-1994 (Box 16, Folder 143-146)
  - Low and Moderate-Income Housing Finance Task Force - Kirsten Moy, 1990-1992 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  - Market for Capital Loans Among New York City Nonprofit Organizations, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 148)
  - Marris, Peter and Martin Rein, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 149)
  - Midwest Center for Labor Research (MCLR), 1994 (Box 17, Folder 150)
  - Massey, Douglas, 1987-1992 (Box 17, Folder 151)
  - Media - Public Will Session of Urban Poverty Program retreat, 1986-1995 (Box 17, Folder 152-153)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) - Evaluation of Self-Employment Investment Demonstration (SEID), 1989-1992 (Box 17, Folder 154)
  - Mead, Lawrence, undated (Box 17, Folder 155)
  - Mega-Cities Project, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 156)
  - John Merck Fund, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 157)
  - Metropolitan Affairs Corporation, 1988-1992 (Box 17, Folder 158)
  - Midwest Center for Labor Research (MCLR), 1994 (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Minority business and entrepreneurship, 1965-1972 (Box 18, Folder 160)
  - Minority funding, 1976-1993 (Box 18, Folder 161)
  - University of California Los Angeles - Minority entrepreneur study, 1989-1993 (Box 18, Folder 162-163)
  - Ford Foundation Mission Statement, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 164)
  - Modification of Program Actions - Copies of letters, 1992-1993 (Box 18, Folder 165)
  - Ms. Foundation for Women - Collaborative Fund for Women's Economic Development, 1988-1995 (Box 18, Folder 166-168)
  - North American Development Bank (NADBank), 1994 (Box 19, Folder 169)
  - National Association of Community Development Loan Funds (NACDLF), 1991-1992 (Box 19, Folder 170)
  - National Center for the Early Childhood Workforce (NCECW), 1994-1995 (Box 19, Folder 171)
  - National Congress for Community Economic Development (NCCED), 1989-1993 (Box 19, Folder 172)
  - National Community Reinvestment Coalition (NCRC), 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 173)
  - National Council of La Raza (NCLR), 1992-1994 (Box 19, Folder 174)
  - National Council for Urban Economic Development (CUED), 1984-1994 (Box 19, Folder 175-176)
  - National Federation of Community Development Credit Unions (NFCDCU), 1994 (Box 19, Folder 177)
  - National Foundation for Teaching Entrepreneurship (NFTE), 1988-1991 (Box 19, Folder 178)
  - National Governors Association, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 179)
  - National Housing Institute, 1988-1993 (Box 20, Folder 180)
  - National Housing Law Project (NHLP), 1992-1994 (Box 20, Folder 181-182)
  - National Housing Law Project (NHLP), 1991-1995 (Box 20, Folder 183-184)
  - National Housing Law Project (NHLP) Conference, Chicago, Illinois, 1993-1995; File includes a photo ID pass. The pass is housed in an envelope in the file. (Box 20, Folder 185)
    The Suburban Job-Link Corp photo ID pass in the files was made for Mark Elliott to use.
  - National Housing Partnership Foundation (NHP Foundation), 1991-1992 (Box 20, Folder 186)
  - National Housing Trust, 1991-1995 (Box 21, Folder 187-189)
  - National Housing Trust, 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 190-191)
  - National Institute for Responsible Fatherhood and Family Development (NIRFFD), 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 192)
  - National League of Cities (NLC), 1987-1995 (Box 22, Folder 193-196)
  - National League for Nursing (NLN), 1992 (Box 22, Folder 197)
  - National Training and Information Center (NTIC), 1990-1996 (Box 22, Folder 198)
  - National Urban League, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 199)
  - Neighborhood Capital Corporation (NCC), 1993 (Box 22, Folder 200)
  - Neighborhood and Family Initiative (NFI), 1989-1993 (Box 23, Folder 201-202)
  - Neighborhood Funders Group (NFG) conference, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 203)
  - Neighborhood Housing Services of New York City (NHS), 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 204)
  - New Federalism, Monitoring the, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 205)
  - New Hope Project, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 206)
  - Newman, Oscar, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 207)
  - Foundations in the Newt Era, 1995 September (Box 23, Folder 208)
  - New York City construction industry, 1991 January (Box 23, Folder 209)
  - New York City Housing Partnership, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 210)
  - New York City Partnership - Small builders program, undated (Box 23, Folder 211)
  - New York State housing conference, 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 212)
  - New School, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 213)
  - New York Community Trust - Neighborhood Strategies Project, 1993-1994 (Box 23, Folder 214)
  - Richard Nixon's domestic policies, 1995 January 9 (Box 23, Folder 215)
  - Nonprofit borrowing, undated (Box 23, Folder 216)
  - Nonprofit housing management, 1991-1993 (Box 24, Folder 217)
  - North Carolina preservation, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 218)
  - North Carolina University at Chapel Hill, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 219)
  - Northeast Workforce Center (NWC), 1993-1995 (Box 24, Folder 220)
  - OMB Watch, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 221)
  - 1000 Friends of Oregon, 1994-1995 (Box 24, Folder 222-223)
  - Partnership for Economic Independence, 1990-1993 (Box 24, Folder 224)
  - Pension fund investment, 1991 August 7 (Box 24, Folder 225)
  - Pew Charitable Trusts, 1993 (Box 24, Folder 226)
  - Philanthropy, 1994-1995 (Box 25, Folder 227)
  - Photographs of Mark Elliott, undated (Box 25, Folder 228)
    Images are photograph proofs of Mark Elliott.
  - Poverty perceptions, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 229)
  - Poverty and Race Research Action Council (PRRAC) Poverty and Race, 1992-1996 (Box 25, Folder 230-231)
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting presentation, 1993-1994 (Box 25, Folder 232)
  - Prepayment rules, 1991-1993 (Box 25, Folder 233)
  - Program Related Investments (PRI), 1992-1994 (Box 25, Folder 234)
  - Program development, 1991-1993 (Box 25, Folder 235)
  - Program development - Womens and minorities' concerns, 1991 (Box 25, Folder 236)
  - Role of Program Related Investments (PRI), 1995 August 1 (Box 25, Folder 237)
  - Program initiatives, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 238)
  - Program support - Fiscal Year 1995, 1994 (Box 25, Folder 239)
  - Project Self-Sufficiency, 1988 (Box 25, Folder 240)
  - Property management, 1992 (Box 25, Folder 241)
  - Public sector project, 1994 February 18 (Box 25, Folder 242)
  - Recycling - Diana Dillaway, 1992 (Box 25, Folder 243)
  - Recycling and economic development, 1992 (Box 25, Folder 244)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA), 1990-1995 (Box 26, Folder 245-246)
  - Reinvesting the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 247)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1994-1996 (Box 26, Folder 248)
  - Regional Alliance for Small Contractors, 1992-1993 (Box 26, Folder 249)
  - Donald Riegle's task force, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 250)
  - Rogers, Julie, 1991 September 24 (Box 26, Folder 251)
  - Rohe, William, 1992-1993 (Box 26, Folder 252)
  - Rossi, Peter, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 253)
  - Russian housing, 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 254)
  - San Francisco Development Fund, 1990-1992 (Box 26, Folder 255)
  - United States Department of Labor Secretary's Commission on Achieving Necessary Skills (SCANS) report, 1991 June (Box 26, Folder 256)
  - United States Small Business Administration (SBA) microloan program, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 257)
  - Scherer, Andrew, 1991-1992 (Box 27, Folder 258)
  - Schill, Michael H., 1995 July 15 (Box 27, Folder 259)
  - Section 8 Housing, 1993-1994 (Box 27, Folder 260)
  - Seedco (Structured Employment/Economic Development Corporation), 1986-1994 (Box 27, Folder 261-263)
  - Self-Employment Learning Project (SELP), 1995 (Box 27, Folder 264)
  - Self-employment Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) study, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 265)
  - Shames, Steve, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 266)
  - SIPI, 1992 February 3 (Box 27, Folder 267)
  - Skillman Foundation, undated (Box 27, Folder 268)
  - Social capital, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 269)
  - Sosin, Michael, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 270)
  - South Africa - A community-based development strategy, 1990 January 24 (Box 28, Folder 271)
  - South Carolina Institute on Poverty and Deprivation (SCIPD), 1989-1993 (Box 28, Folder 272-273)
  - Southwest Community Development Initiative, undated (Box 28, Folder 274)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, 1993-1996 (Box 28, Folder 275-277)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, 1992-1994 (Box 28, Folder 278)
  - Speeches - Vaclav Havel, 1994 July 8 (Box 28, Folder 279)
  - Staff retreat - Urban Poverty Program, 1993 (Box 28, Folder 280)
  - Street vendors, 1995 (Box 28, Folder 281)
  - Stegman, Michael, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 282)
  - Suburbanization, undated (Box 29, Folder 283)
  - Surdna Foundation, 1994 (Box 29, Folder 284)
  - Sustainable America, 1995 (Box 29, Folder 285)
  - Defining Sustainable Communities, 1995 (Box 29, Folder 286)
  - Sustainable development, 1994 (Box 29, Folder 287)
  - Swarthmore College, 1992-1993 (Box 29, Folder 288)
  - The Empowerment Network Foundation (TEN), 1995-1996 (Box 29, Folder 289)
  - Transition material - Ford Foundation programming, 1995-1996 (Box 29, Folder 290)
  - Transportation strategies, 1992-1993 (Box 29, Folder 291-292)